# Mikel Kamel

Somerset, NJ 08873 <u>mmk39@njit.edu</u> 609-373-9470

Portfolio: <a href="https://mikelkamel.com">https://mikelkamel.com</a> GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/BigMikeL9">https://github.com/BigMikeL9</a>

### **Summary**

I'm a Web Developer who specializes in Front-End Web Development. I have the ability to design and develop fully responsive static and dynamic websites and Web applications using HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript (ES6+) and React framework.

## **EDUCATION**

New Jersey Institute of Technology (NJIT)
Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering (*Graduated*)

Newark, NJ Summer 2018

# **SKILLS**

- **Programs**: Visual Studio Code, Atom, JetBrains Rider, Adobe Illustrator, Adobe XD, Adobe Photoshop, Git, GitHub, Bitbucket, Jira, Unity3D, AutoCAD, Revit, Civil3D.
- **Programming Languages and Tools**: HTML5, CSS3, Modern JavaScript (ES6+), C#, ReactJS, Redux, Sass, jQuery, Node.js, Express, npm, yarn, Babel, Webpack, Parcel.

#### **Interpersonal Skills:**

- High proficiency using HTML5, CSS3, and Modern JavaScript (ES6+) programming languages.
- Hands on experience using CSS3 and JavaScript frameworks and libraries, Sass/SCSS, ReactJS, Redux.
- Experience with server-side application scripting using Node.js and Express framework.
- High understanding of Object-Oriented programming and Asynchronous behavior in JavaScript.
- Highly experienced with implementation of AJAX Calls, Promises, Async/Await, and RESTful APIs.
- Experienced in building responsive websites and web applications that follow W3C markup and accessibility standards.
- High proficiency using version control and Git flows.
- Experience using visual design tools, Adobe Illustrator, Adobe XD, and Adobe Photoshop.
- Excellent experience in debugging, optimization, and refining code.

- Knowledge in all aspects of front-end web development, from designing to programming.
- Proficiency in writing clear, reusable, concise code and documenting implemented features.
- Great capacity for learning new languages and implementing new programming patterns.
- Highly skilled using Unity3D and C# language.
- Ability to constantly learn and stay in touch with evolving standards and development technologies.
- Experience working on tight schedules, to meet with clients' deadlines and expectations.
- Ability to work well in a cooperative, multi-disciplinary team environment to develop and maintain new awesome features.
- Ability to quickly adapt to changing situations and take on new challenges.

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

• Front-End Web Developer, November 2021 to Current Astriata

As a Front-End Web Developer, I worked closely with designers, developers, and clients on various projects in the association, healthcare, nonprofit, higher-education, government, and B2B sectors.

- Rewrote HTML to meet industry and company standards for SEO, Accessibility, and W3C requirements.
- Work closely with designers, developers, and clients to meet project requirement, goals, and desired functionality.
- Improved the workflow for 3 different major projects by implementing a 6-to-8-point checklist for all backlog tasks, which reduced the site plans preparations time by half.
- Ensured efficient web development by supporting designers and Back-End developers while resolving website performance issues.
- Tested, debugged and shipped 10s of 1000s of lines of code to various development teams.
- Developed stunning visual elements of web applications by translating UI/UX design wireframes into code while producing high quality, reusable markup using HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, and Third-party libraries.
- Identified and implemented dynamic web solutions in accordance to company standards and best practices.
- Led troubleshooting, fixed bugs and other issues, and updated sites throughout production lifecycle.
- Worked with designers, project manager, and back-end developers to achieve design goals, and directly helped advance the organization's design system documentation.
- Developed 100% reusable code and libraries for future use.

# • Web Developer/ Gameplay Programmer, December 2020 to Current

- Single-handedly designed and developed multiple websites and web applications for different clients based on their needs, ranging from Portfolios, Photography, Medical, Games and Gallery websites/applications, all by utilizing HTML5, CSS3, JavaScript, and React Framework.
- Reworked multiple client websites, making them fully responsive, while also following the Web Accessibility Standards.
- Created Audits for multiple client websites and Web Applications to address SEO, Accessibility, W3C and performance issues.
- Developed numerous fully functional Unity3D games for different clients looking to build their dream games. Game types included a shooting, a strategy, an endless runner, and a horror game.

# • Design Engineer, September 2019 to December 2020 Gladstone Design, Inc.

Design Engineer who worked on various types of projects including Residential, Corporate & Commercial, Energy, Golf Course & Resort, Institutional, and Public, using AutoCAD, Civil 3D and Bentley PondPack.

- Improved the workflow for 3 different major projects by implementing a 6-to-8-point checklist for all backlog tasks, which reduced the site plans preparations time by half.
- Designed an economical Stormwater system for a client's private property which cut the price of constructing and maintaining the system by 60%.
- Created a new employee mentoring program, and helped new coworkers learn the industry's best practices.
- Stepped up when 2 projects were scheduled to be submitted on the same week and on a tight schedule, which resulted in both projects being submitted right on time all while meeting with the clients' requirements.
- Debugged and upgraded Stormwater Management systems to reduce runoff of rainwater and improve water quality, using PondPack.
- Developed site plans for different clients, including Site Dimension, Site Grading, Utility, Landscape, Lighting, Soil Erosion Control, Roadway/Utility profiles, Details and Drainage Area plans.
- Designed and improved Signage/Striping and Fire Truck turning plans.
- Engaged in developing Rendered Site, Utility plans prior to board, client, bid etc. meetings.
- Researched a wide variety of land Zoning, Easements, Setbacks based on each Township's regulations.
- Miscellaneous field work experience including site visits, soil testing/logging, and inspections.
- Construction Inspector, September 2018 to August 2019 Geo-Technology Associates, Inc.

As a Construction Inspector, I inspected construction work to ensure compliance with building standards and project specifications, documented inspections while reporting any issues, and determined the quality of materials being used through testing.

- Improved the workflow on multiple construction sites while making sure everything is moving according to plan and budget.
- Assisted and worked with Geotechnical Engineers in the design and evaluation of different construction sites.
- Performed geotechnical engineering analyses and report preparations.
- Investigated soils for issues such as slope and erosion settlements.
- Collected soil samples from different sites using bores and test pits.
- Lab testing of material obtained from the field.
- Documentation and reporting of field inspections.

# • Intern, Construction Engineer, July 2018 to August 2018

Worked over the summer as a construction engineer at ORASCOM Construction in Egypt, in a project called The Mansoura Project. The project involved the construction of residential buildings for the army.

- Assisted civil engineers in the design and improvements for the project, solutions
  for issues that we faced on the site during site visitations, attended meetings and
  discussed the project details with other civil engineers, worked under a great civil
  engineer and gained experience on how to supervise the project and communicate
  with the workers.
- Gained more experience in plan reading, as well as preparation of plans with improvements made to them.
- Learned more about cost-of-material estimation, report and document tracking, on-site project visits, project documentation, and building permit applications.
- Managed construction workers as they performed their jobs, and guided them in any problems they encountered.
- Gained more experience in the field of geotechnical engineering by performing geotechnical investigations in connection with the project.